CURRICULUM VITAE

PERSONAL INFORMATION

Name: Darlinda Fatmata Jiba

Date of Birth: 19th March 1991

Nationality: Sierra Leonean

Profession: Medical Doctor

Contact Details: Email: darlindajiba.dj@gmail.com Phone Number: +23278236153

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Dr Darlinda Fatmata Jiba is a Sierra Leonean Medical Doctor with over five (5) years of work experience in fields of Internal Medicine, Infectious Diseases and Public Health. She has vast knowledge on Antimicrobial Resistance and care of HIV, Tuberculosis and Sexually Transmitted Infections care and other common Infectious Diseases in Sierra Leone.

At present she is the only female registrar in the department of Internal Medicine, University of Sierra Leone Teaching Hospitals Complex and offers mentorship to Medical Officers and nurses at Connaught Teaching Hospital's HIV center. She also plays a pivotal role in ensuring that high quality clinical standards are maintained in the management of hospitalized patients with HIV at Connaught Teaching Hospital.

Currently, she leads the Antimicrobial Stewardship Sub-Committee at the national referral hospital, a unit that promotes appropriate use of antimicrobials and prevention of antimicrobial resistance.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Antimicrobial Stewardship (AMS) Sub-committee lead- September 2021 to Date Responsibilities:

 Coordinates all AMS activities including antimicrobial audits and healthcare-associated infections surveillance, at the National Referral Hospital (Connaught Teaching Hospital)

- Provide mentorship and supportive supervision to clinicians on optimizing antimicrobial use.
- Develop and implement measures that support rational antimicrobial use.
- Generate, analyse and utilize AMS data in real time.

Registrar (Internal Medicine)- 12th April 2021 to Date

As a registrar, we do mandatory rotations in Infectious Diseases, Cardiology, Nephrology, Pulmonology, Dermatology, Endocrinology, Gastroenterology, Laboratory Medicine, Psychiatry, Radiology and Neurology units and any other two (2) units within the domains of Internal Medicine.

Responsibilities:

- Ensures effective and efficient management of admitted in any unit.
- Supervises medical officers, house officers and medical students.
- Perform and teach clinical procedures.
- Coordinates academic activities.
- Coordinate routine data collection and analysis of unit's morbidity and mortality
- Coordinate unit's research activities.

Research Coordinator Case management Pillar, National COVID-19 Emergency Response Center (NACOVERC): 1st May 2020- 30th March 2021

Responsibilities:

- 1. Development of data sets used in all COVID-19 treatment and community centers (done in collaboration with clinicians and public health experts)
- 2. Real time managementand dissemination of all data collected in COVID-19 treatment and community centers
- 3. Training and supervision of data clerks in all COVID-19 treatment and community centers
- 4. Basic analysis of data generated in all COVID-19 treatment and community centers to be utilized by Clinicians and other stakeholders for informed decision making
- 5. Coordinate weekly Case management Pillar scientific meetings for all clinicians COVID-19 treatment centres
- 6. Coordinate all research activities within the Case management pillar

Medical Officer- 8th April 2019-30th April 2020

Responsibilities:

- 1. Led the management of HIV and related conditions including Advanced HIV Disease at Connaught Teaching Hospital HIV center (the national referral center for advanced HIV care)
- 2. Capacity building of clinical staff in the unit
- 3. Organized HIV outreach programs
- 4. Monitoring and Evaluation of unit activities
- 5. Supportive supervision and mentorship of clinical staff
- 6. Provided services (including STI services, safe sex and general health promotion) to various support groups dealing with children and adolescent living with HIV, female sex workers and the Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, and Transgender (LGBT) community.

House Officer- 3rd April 2017 to 30th March 2019

Responsibilities:

Rotated through various medical specialties at Connaught Teaching Hospital, Princess Christian Maternity Hospital and Ola During Children's Hospital and delivered community care on HIV and other Sexually Transmitted Infections and provided health services for LGBTQs in Sierra Leone on voluntary basis.

EDUCATION

- April 2021 to date: In residency training for Membership of West African College of Physicians
- September 2009-November 2016: MB, ChB: University of Sierra Leone

TRAININGS

- July 2023, Research Fellowship training at Fogarty International Centre, National Health Institute
- January 2023, Advanced Retroviral Disease (screening and management)
- February 2020, National Viral Hepatitis B & C guidelines in Sierra Leone
- May 2020, Certificate training as trainer of trainees on COVID-19 Prevention,
 Screening and Management
- March 2020, COVID-19 training (Case detection and Surveillance and management)
- December 2019, WHO Massive Open Online Course on Implementation Research with a focus on Infectious Diseases of poverty

- September 2018, Training on Mass Casualty Training by King's Health Partners
- April 2017, Training on Emergency Triage Assessment and Treatment plus Admission care for Sick Children (ETAT PLUS. By Royal College of Paediatrics and child health, Ministry of Health and Sanitation, and King's Partnership
- September 2014, Ebola training (screening and management)

PROFESSIONAL MEMBERSHIPS

- Fellow at Fogarty International Centre, National Health Institute
- Member of the Sierra Leone Medical and Dental Association
- Junior Doctors Association of Sierra Leone
- Registered with Medical and Dental Council of Sierra Leone

PUBLICATIONS

I have over eighteen 24 publications, 21 of which have been published in peer reviewed journals. (Link to publications on PubMed: https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/?term=jiba+df)

- Lakoh S, Orefuwa E, Kamara MN, Jiba DF, Kamara JB, Kpaka S, Denning DW. The burden of serious fungal infections in Sierra Leone: a national estimate. Ther Adv Infect Dis. 2021 Jun 30;8:20499361211027996. doi: 10.1177/20499361211027996. PMID: 34262759; PMCID: PMC8252340.
- Lakoh S, Yi L, Russell JBW, Zhang J, Sevalie S, Zhao Y, Kanu JS, Liu P, Conteh SK, Williams CEE, Barrie U, Sheku MG, Jalloh MB, Adekanmbi O, Jiba DF, Kamara MN, et al. The burden of surgical site infections and related antibiotic resistance in two geographic regions of Sierra Leone: a prospective study. Ther Adv Infect Dis. 2022 Dec 7;9:20499361221135128. doi: 10.1177/20499361221135128. PMID: 36518726; PMCID: PMC9742716.
- 3. Lakoh S, Kanu JS, Conteh SK, Russell JBW, Sevalie S, Williams CEE, Barrie U, Kabia AK, Conteh F, Jalloh MB, Deen GF, Kabba MS, Lebbie A, Kamara IF, Fofanah BD, Maruta A, Kallon C, Sahr F, Samai M, Adekanmbi O, Yi L, Guo X, Kamara RZ, Jiba DF, et al. High levels of surgical antibiotic prophylaxis: Implications for hospital-based antibiotic stewardship in Sierra Leone. Antimicrob Steward Healthc Epidemiol. 2022 Jul 7;2(1):e111. doi: 10.1017/ash.2022.252. PMID: 36483422; PMCID: PMC9726495.

- 4. Lakoh S, Yi L, Sevalie S, Guo X, Adekanmbi O, Smalle IO, Williams N, Barrie U, Koroma C, Zhao Y, Kamara MN, Cummings-John C, Jiba DF, et al. Incidence and risk factors of surgical site infections and related antibiotic resistance in Freetown, Sierra Leone: a prospective cohort study. Antimicrob Resist Infect Control. 2022 Feb 21;11(1):39. doi: 10.1186/s13756-022-01078-y. PMID: 35189952; PMCID: PMC8862228.
- 5. Lakoh S, **Jiba DF**, Baldeh M, Adekanmbi O, Barrie U, et al. Impact of COVID-19 on Tuberculosis Case Detection and Treatment Outcomes in Sierra Leone. Trop Med Infect Dis. 2021 Aug 19;6(3):154. doi: 10.3390/tropicalmed6030154. PMID: 34449755; PMCID: PMC8396336.
- 6. Yendewa GA, Lakoh S, Jiba DF, Yendewa SA, et al. Hepatitis B Virus and Tuberculosis Are Associated with Increased Noncommunicable Disease Risk among Treatment-Naïve People with HIV: Opportunities for Prevention, Early Detection and Management of Comorbidities in Sierra Leone. J Clin Med. 2022 Jun 16;11(12):3466. doi: 10.3390/jcm11123466. PMID: 35743539; PMCID: PMC9225550.
- Yendewa GA, Lakoh S, Yendewa SA, Bangura K, Tabernilla A, Patiño L, Jiba DF, Vandy AO, et al. Characterizing HIV-1 Genetic Subtypes and Drug Resistance Mutations among Children, Adolescents and Pregnant Women in Sierra Leone. Genes (Basel). 2021 Aug 26;12(9):1314. doi: 10.3390/genes12091314. PMID: 34573296; PMCID: PMC8469552.
- 8. Yendewa GA, Poveda E, Lakoh S, Yendewa SA, **Jiba DF**, Salgado-Barreira A, Sahr F, Salata RA. High Prevalence of Late-Stage Disease in Newly Diagnosed Human Immunodeficiency Virus Patients in Sierra Leone. Open Forum Infect Dis. 2018 Aug 23;5(9):ofy208. doi: 10.1093/ofid/ofy208. PMID: 30191158; PMCID: PMC6121223.
- Lakoh S, Jiba DF, Vandy AO, Poveda E, Adekanmbi O, et al. Assessing eligibility for differentiated service delivery, HIV services utilization and virologic outcomes of adult HIV-infected patients in Sierra Leone: a pre-implementation analysis. Glob Health Action. 2021 Jan 1;14(1):1947566. doi: 10.1080/16549716.2021.1947566. PMID: 34404330; PMCID: PMC8381912.
- 10. Lakoh S, Firima E, **Jiba DF,** Kamara MN, Gashau W, et al. Prevalence of sero-markers and non-invasive assessment of liver cirrhosis in patients with Hepatitis B virus infection in Freetown, Sierra Leone: a cross-sectional study.

- BMC Gastroenterol. 2021 Aug 9;21(1):320. doi: 10.1186/s12876-021-01892-5. PMID: 34372775; PMCID: PMC8353767.
- 11. Lakoh S, Firima E, **Jiba DF**, Kamara MN, Gashau W, et al. Prevalence of sero-markers and non-invasive assessment of liver cirrhosis in patients with Hepatitis B virus infection in Freetown, Sierra Leone: a cross-sectional study. BMC Gastroenterol. 2021 Aug 9;21(1):320. doi: 10.1186/s12876-021-01892-5. PMID: 34372775; PMCID: PMC8353767.
- 12. Lakoh S, Firima E, Williams CEE, Conteh SK, Jalloh MB, Sheku MG, Adekanmbi O, Sevalie S, Kamara SA, Kamara MAS, Barrie U, Kamara GN, Yi L, Guo X, Haffner C, Kamara MN, Jiba DF, Namanaga ES, et al. An Intra-COVID-19 Assessment of Hand Hygiene Facility, Policy and Staff Compliance in Two Hospitals in Sierra Leone: Is There a Difference between Regional and Capital City Hospitals? Trop Med Infect Dis. 2021 Nov 29;6(4):204. doi: 10.3390/tropicalmed6040204. PMID: 34941660; PMCID: PMC8705290.
- 13. Lakoh S, Firima E, **Jiba DF**, Sesay M, Conteh MM, Deen GF. Low partner testing in high HIV prevalence setting in Freetown, Sierra Leone: a retrospective study. BMC Res Notes. 2019 Sep 24;12(1):629. doi: 10.1186/s13104-019-4662-9. PMID: 31551091; PMCID: PMC6760048.
- 14. Lakoh S, Adekanmbi O, **Jiba DF**, Deen GF, Gashau W, Sevalie S, Klein EY. Antibiotic use among hospitalized adult patients in a setting with limited laboratory infrastructure in Freetown Sierra Leone, 2017–2018. Int J Infect Dis. 2020 Jan;90:71–76. doi: 10.1016/j.ijid.2019.10.022. Epub 2019 Oct 23. PMID: 31655112.
- 15. Lakoh S, **Jiba DF**, Kanu JE, Poveda E, Salgado-Barreira A,et al. Causes of hospitalization and predictors of HIV-associated mortality at the main referral hospital in Sierra Leone: a prospective study. BMC Public Health. 2019 Oct 21;19(1):1320. doi: 10.1186/s12889-019-7614-3. PMID: 31638941; PMCID: PMC6805411.
- 16. Lakoh S, Jiba DF, Adekanmbi O, Poveda E,et al. Diagnosis and treatment outcomes of adult tuberculosis in an urban setting with high HIV prevalence in Sierra Leone: A retrospective study. Int J Infect Dis. 2020 Jul;96:112–118. doi: 10.1016/j.ijid.2020.04.038. Epub 2020 Apr 24. PMID: 32339724.
- 17. Lakoh S, Rickman H, Sesay M, Kenneh S, Burke R, Baldeh M, Jiba DF, Tejan YS, et al. Prevalence and mortality of cryptococcal disease in adults with advanced

- HIV in an urban tertiary hospital in Sierra Leone: a prospective study. BMC Infect Dis. 2020 Feb 14;20(1):141. doi: 10.1186/s12879-020-4862-x. PMID: 32059703; PMCID: PMC7023785.
- 18. Mushi MF, Zaki SM, Penney ROS, et al. Diagnostic Options forPulmonary Fungal Diseases in Africa. ERJ Open Res 2023; in press (https://doi.org/10.1183/23120541.00397-2022).
- 19. Mustapha J, Namanga ES, Idriss B, Sesay D, **Jiba DF**, Russell JBW, Vandy MJ, Deen GF, Yendewa GA, Lakoh S. Ophthalmic Manifestations among HIV Patients at the Main Tertiary Hospital in Freetown, Sierra Leone: A Cross-Sectional Study. *Venereology*. 2022; 1(2):161-169. https://doi.org/10.3390/venereology1020011
- 20. Lakoh, Sulaiman & Jiba, Darlinda & Baldeh, Mamadu & Vandy, Alren & Benya, Hassan & Lado, Marta & Sevalie, Stephen & Yendewa, George & SAHR, Foday. (2020). Sepsis and septic shock in COVID-19: a scoping review of the research data. 10.21203/rs.3.rs-30474/v1.
- 21. Lakoh, Sulaiman. Darlinda F. Jiba, Mohamed Bawoh (2017). Ownership and Use of Insecticide Treated Nets by Pregnant Women at Dworzark Community in Freetown, Sierra Leone. TEXILA INTERNATIONAL JOURNAL OF PUBLIC HEALTH. 5. 178-190. 10.21522/TIJPH.2013.05.04.Art018.

REFERENCES

Dr. Sulaiman Lakoh
Lecturer/Consultant Physician (Infectious Diseases), University of Sierra Leone Teaching
Hospitals Complex
Executive Director, Sustainable Health Systems
Lakoh2009@gmail.com
+23278287492

Dr. Gibrilla Fadlu-Deen
Lecturer/ Specialist Internal Medicine
Connaught Teaching hospital Complex
Freetown Sierra Leone
gibrilladeen1960@yahoo.com
+23276865597